<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><quotes><quote id="0" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Now what I contend is that my body is my own, at least I have always so regarded it. If I do harm through my experimenting with it, it is I who suffer, not the state.</quote><quote id="1" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">"I haven't a particle of confidence in a man who has no redeeming petty vices whatsoever."</quote><quote id="2" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">I'll risk forty dollars that he can outjump any frog in Calaveras county.</quote><quote id="3" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">I don't see no p'ints about that frog that's any better'n any other frog.</quote><quote id="4" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">He was ignorant of the commonest accomplishments of youth. He could not even lie.</quote><quote id="5" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Soap and education are not as sudden as a massacre, but they are more deadly in the long run.</quote><quote id="6" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Tomorrow night I appear for the first time before a Boston audience — 4000 critics.</quote><quote id="7" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">He is now fast rising from affluence to poverty.</quote><quote id="8" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Barring that natural expression of villainy which we all have, the man looked honest enough.</quote><quote id="9" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Formerly, if you killed a man, it was possible that you were insane—but now, if you, having friends and money, kill a man, it is "evidence" that you are a lunatic.</quote><quote id="10" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Is not this insanity plea becoming rather common? Is it not so common that the reader confidently expects to see it offered in every criminal case that comes before the courts? [...] Really, what we want now, is not laws against crime, but a law against "insanity".</quote><quote id="11" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">It [the press] has scoffed at religion till it has made scoffing popular. It has defended official criminals, on party pretexts, until it has created a United States Senate whose members are incapable of determining what crime against law and the dignity of their own body is—they are so morally blind—and it has made light of dishonesty till we have as a result a Congress which contracts to work for a certain sum and then deliberately steals additional wages out of the public pocket and is pained and surprised that anybody should worry about a little thing like that.</quote><quote id="12" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Benjamin Franklin did a great many notable things for his country, and made her young name to be honored in many lands as the mother of such a son. It is not the idea of this memoir to ignore that or cover it up. No; the simple idea of it is to snub those pretentious maxims of his, which he worked up with a great show of originality out of truisms that had become wearisome platitudes as early as the dispersion from Babel.</quote><quote id="13" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">This poor little one-horse town.</quote><quote id="14" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">All men have heard of the Mormon Bible, but few except the "elect" have seen it, or, at least, taken the trouble to read it. I brought away a copy from Salt Lake. The book is a curiosity to me, it is such a pretentious affair, and yet so "slow," so sleepy; such an insipid mess of inspiration. It is chloroform in print. If Joseph Smith composed this book, the act was a miracle — keeping awake while he did it was, at any rate. If he, according to tradition, merely translated it from certain ancient and mysteriously-engraved plates of copper, which he declares he found under a stone in an out-of-the-way locality, the work of translating was equally a miracle, for the same reason.</quote><quote id="15" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">A baby is an inestimable blessing and bother.</quote><quote id="16" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">The funniest things are the forbidden.</quote><quote id="17" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">We haven't all had the good fortune to be ladies; we haven't all been generals, or poets, or statesmen; but when the toast works down to the babies, we stand on common ground.</quote><quote id="18" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Among the three or four million cradles now rocking in the land are some which this nation would preserve for ages as sacred things, if we could know which ones they are.</quote><quote id="19" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">"Reader, suppose you were an idiot. And suppose you were a member of Congress. But I repeat myself."</quote><quote id="20" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Be respectful to your superiors, if you have any.</quote><quote id="21" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">When the doctrine of allegiance to party can utterly up-end a man's moral constitution and make a temporary fool of him besides, what excuse are you going to offer for preaching it, teaching it, extending it, perpetuating it? Shall you say, the best good of the country demands allegiance to party? Shall you also say it demands that a man kick his truth and his conscience into the gutter, and become a mouthing lunatic, besides?</quote><quote id="22" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Loyalty to petrified opinions never yet broke a chain or freed a human soul in "this" world — and never "will".</quote><quote id="23" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">He [George Washington Cable] has taught me to abhor and detest the Sabbath day and hunt up new and troublesome ways to dishonor it.</quote><quote id="24" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">An experienced, industrious, ambitious, and often quite picturesque liar.</quote><quote id="25" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">It does look as if Massachusetts were in a fair way to embarrass me with kindnesses this year. In the first place, a Massachusetts judge has just decided in open court that a Boston publisher may sell, not only his own property in a free and unfettered way, but also may as freely sell property which does not belong to him but to me; property which he has not bought and which I have not sold. Under this ruling I am now advertising that judge's homestead for sale, and, if I make as good a sum out of it as I expect, I shall go on and sell out the rest of his property.</quote><quote id="26" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">As I slowly grow wise I briskly grow cautious.</quote><quote id="27" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">A circle is a round straight line with a hole in the middle.</quote><quote id="28" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">The difference between the "almost right" word and the "right" word is really a large matter—'tis the difference between the lightning-bug and the lightning.</quote><quote id="29" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Weather is a literary specialty, and no untrained hand can turn out a good article on it.</quote><quote id="30" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">I am opposed to millionaires, but it would be dangerous to offer me the position.</quote><quote id="31" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref=""> If you tell the truth you don't have to remember anything.</quote><quote id="32" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">James Ross Clemens, a cousin of mine, was seriously ill two or three weeks ago in London, but is well now. The report of my illness grew out of his illness; "the report of my death was an exaggeration."</quote><quote id="33" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">A round man cannot be expected to fit in a square hole right away. He must have time to modify his shape.</quote><quote id="34" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">[Citing a familiar "American joke":] In Boston they ask, How much does he know? In New York, How much is he worth? In Philadelphia, Who were his parents?</quote><quote id="35" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Humor is the great thing, the saving thing. The minute it crops up, all our hardnesses yield, all our irritations and resentments flit away and a sunny spirit takes their place.</quote><quote id="36" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Get your facts first, and then you can distort them as much as you please.</quote><quote id="37" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">I was sorry to have my name mentioned as one of the great authors, because they have a sad habit of dying off. Chaucer is dead, Spencer is dead, so is Milton, so is Shakespeare, and I’m not feeling so well myself.</quote><quote id="38" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">It is wonderful, the power of a faith like that, that can make multitudes upon multitudes of the old and weak and the young and frail enter without hesitation or complaint upon such incredible journeys and endure the resultant miseries without repining. It is done in love, or it is done in fear; I do not know which it is. No matter what the impulse is, the act born of it is beyond imagination marvelous to our kind of people, the cold whites.</quote><quote id="39" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Definition of a classic — something that everybody wants to have read and nobody wants to read.</quote><quote id="40" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">"The silent colossal National Lie that is the support and confederate of all the tyrannies and shams and inequalities and unfairnesses that afflict the peoples — that is the one to throw bricks and sermons at."</quote><quote id="41" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Your race, in its poverty, has unquestionably one really effective weapon—laughter. Power, Money, Persuasion, Supplication, Persecution—these can lift at a colossal humbug,—push it a little—crowd it a little—weaken it a little, century by century: but only Laughter can blow it to rags and atoms at a blast. Against the assault of Laughter nothing can stand.</quote><quote id="42" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">{{Anchor|Whose_property}}"Whose property is my body? Probably mine. I so regard it. If I experiment with it, who must be answerable? I, not the State. If I choose injudiciously, does the State die? Oh no."</quote><quote id="43" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">...[H]eaven for climate, Hell for society.</quote><quote id="44" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">also given as: Heaven for climate, Hell for companionship.</quote><quote id="45" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Honesty is the best policy - when there is money in it.</quote><quote id="46" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">The Blessings-of-Civilization Trust, wisely and cautiously administered, is a Daisy. There is more money in it, more territory, more sovereignty, and other kinds of emolument, than there is in any other game that is played. But Christendom has been playing it badly of late years, and must certainly suffer by it, in my opinion. She has been so eager to get every stake that appeared on the green cloth, that the People who Sit in Darkness have noticed it -- they have noticed it, and have begun to show alarm. They have become suspicious of the Blessings of Civilization.</quote><quote id="47" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">"Always do right. This will gratify some people, and astonish the rest."</quote><quote id="48" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">To create man was a fine and original idea; but to add the sheep was a tautology.</quote><quote id="49" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Oh, dear me, how unspeakably funny and owlishly idiotic and grotesque was that "plagiarism" farce! As if there was much of anything in any human utterance, oral or written, "except" plagiarism! "The kernal, the soul —</quote><quote id="50" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Man has been here 32,000 years. That it took a hundred million years to prepare the world for him is proof that that is what it was done for. I suppose it is, I dunno. If the Eiffel Tower were now representing the world's age, the skin of paint on the pinnacle-knob at its summit would represent man's share of that age; and anybody would perceive that the skin was what the tower was built for. I reckon they would, I dunno.</quote><quote id="51" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">To put it in rude, plain, unpalatable words — "true" patriotism, real patriotism: loyalty not to a Family and a Fiction, but a loyalty to the Nation itself!
..."Remember this, take this to heart, live by it, die for it if necessary: that our patriotism is medieval, outworn, obsolete; that the modern patriotism, the true patriotism, the only rational patriotism, is "loyalty to the Nation ALL the time, loyalty to the Government when it deserves it."" [Czar Nicholas II]</quote><quote id="52" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">He is a stranger to me, but he is a most remarkable man — and I am the other one. Between us, we cover all knowledge; he knows all that can be known, and I know the rest.</quote><quote id="53" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">The only reason why God created man is because he was disappointed with the monkey.</quote><quote id="54" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">A powerful agent is the right word. Whenever we come upon one of those intensely right words in a book or a newspaper the resulting effect is physical as well as spiritual, and electrically prompt.</quote><quote id="55" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Customs do not concern themselves with right or wrong or reason. But they have to be obeyed; one reasons all around them until he is tired, but he must not transgress them, it is sternly forbidden.</quote><quote id="56" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Laws are sand, customs are rock. Laws can be evaded and punishment escaped, but an openly transgressed custom brings sure punishment.</quote><quote id="57" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">"In God We Trust." Now then, after that legend had remained there forty years or so, unchallenged and doing no harm to anybody, the President suddenly "threw a fit" the other day, as the popular expression goes, and ordered that remark to be removed from our coinage. 
Mr. Carnegie granted that the matter was not of consequence, that a coin had just exactly the same value without the legend as with it, and he said he had no fault to find with Mr. Roosevelt's action but only with his expressed reasons for the act. The President had ordered the suppression of that motto because a coin carried the name of God into improper places, and this was a profanation of the Holy Name. Carnegie said the name of God is used to being carried into improper places everywhere and all the time, and that he thought the President's reasoning rather weak and poor. 
I thought the same, and said, "But that is just like the President. If you will notice, he is very much in the habit of furnishing a poor reason for his acts while there is an excellent reason staring him in the face, which he overlooks. "There was a good reason for removing that motto; there was, indeed, an unassailably good reason — in the fact that the motto stated a lie. If this nation has ever trusted in God, that time has gone by; for nearly half a century almost its entire trust has been in the Republican party and the dollar–mainly the dollar." I recognize that I am only making an assertion and furnishing no proof; I am sorry, but this is a habit of mine; sorry also that I am not alone in it; everybody seems to have this disease. 
Take an instance: the removal of the motto fetched out a clamor from the pulpit; little groups and small conventions of clergymen gathered themselves together all over the country, and one of these little groups, consisting of twenty-two ministers, put up a prodigious assertion unbacked by any quoted statistics and passed it unanimously in the form of a resolution: the assertion, to wit, that this is a Christian country. Why, Carnegie, so is hell. Those clergymen know that, inasmuch as "Strait is the way and narrow is the gate, and few — few — are they that enter in thereat" has had the natural effect of making hell the only really prominent Christian community in any of the worlds; but we don't brag of this and certainly it is not proper to brag and boast that America is a Christian country when we all know that certainly five-sixths of our population could not enter in at the narrow gate.</quote><quote id="58" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">"The rule is perfect: in all matters of opinion our adversaries are insane. "</quote><quote id="59" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">I have been complimented many times and they always embarrass me; I always feel that they have not said enough.</quote><quote id="60" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Thunder is good, thunder is impressive; but it is lightning that does the work.</quote><quote id="61" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">When even the brightest mind in our world has been trained up from childhood in a superstition of any kind, it will never be possible for that mind, in its maturity, to examine sincerely, dispassionately, and conscientiously any evidence or any circumstance which shall seem to cast a doubt upon the validity of that superstition. I doubt if I could do it myself.</quote><quote id="62" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Adam's "temperament" was the first command the Deity ever issued to a human being on this planet. And it was the only command Adam would "never" be able to disobey. It said, "Be weak, be water, be characterless, be cheaply persuadable." The later command, to let the fruit alone, was certain to be disobeyed. Not by Adam himself, but by his "temperament" — which he did not create and had no authority over.</quote><quote id="63" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">The easy confidence with which I know another man's religion is folly teaches me to suspect that my own is also.</quote><quote id="64" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">You tell me whar a man gits his corn pone, en I'll tell you what his 'pinions is.</quote><quote id="65" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">We all do no end of feeling, and we mistake it for thinking. And out of it we get an aggregation which we consider a boon. Its name is public opinion. It is held in reverence. Some think it the voice of God.</quote><quote id="66" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">The lack of money is the root of all evil.</quote><quote id="67" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Clothes make the man. Naked people have little or no influence on society.</quote><quote id="68" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">"Always acknowledge a fault frankly. This will throw those in authority off their guard and give you opportunity to commit more."</quote><quote id="69" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">"Humor must not professedly teach, and it must not professedly preach, but it must do both if it would live forever. By forever, I mean thirty years."</quote><quote id="70" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">A critic never made or killed a book or a play. The people themselves are the final judges. It is their opinion that counts. After all, the final test is truth. But the trouble is that most writers regard truth as their most valuable possession and therefore are most economical in its use.</quote><quote id="71" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">It is curious that physical courage should be so common in the world, and moral courage so rare.</quote><quote id="72" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Jesus died to save men — a small thing for an immortal to do, &amp; didn't save many, anyway; but if he had been damned for the race that would have been act of a size proper to a god, &amp; would have saved the whole race. However, why should anybody want to save the human race, or damn it either? Does God want its society? Does Satan?</quote><quote id="73" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">A man is never more truthful than when he acknowledges himself a liar.</quote><quote id="74" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">I do not take any credit to my better-balanced head because I never went crazy on Presbyterianism. We go too slow for that. You never see us ranting and shouting and tearing up the ground, You never heard of a Presbyterian going crazy on religion. Notice us, and you will see how we do. We get up of a Sunday morning and put on the best harness we have got and trip cheerfully down town; we subside into solemnity and enter the church; we stand up and duck our heads and bear down on a hymn book propped on the pew in front when the minister prays; we stand up again while our hired choir are singing, and look in the hymn book and check off the verses to see that they don't shirk any of the stanzas; we sit silent and grave while the minister is preaching, and count the waterfalls and bonnets furtively, and catch flies; we grab our hats and bonnets when the benediction is begun; when it is finished, we shove, so to speak. No frenzy, no fanaticism --no skirmishing; everything perfectly serene. You never see any of us Presbyterians getting in a sweat about religion and trying to massacre the neighbors. Let us all be content with the tried and safe old regular religions, and take no chances on wildcat.</quote><quote id="75" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">"Thousands of geniuses live and die undiscovered — either by themselves or by others." But for the Civil War, Lincoln and Grant and Sherman and Sheridan would not have been discovered, nor have risen into notice. ... I have touched upon this matter in a small book which I wrote a generation ago and which I have not published as yet — "Captain Stormfield's Visit to Heaven". When Stormfield arrived in heaven he ... was told that ... a shoemaker ... was the most prodigious military genius the planet had ever produced.</quote><quote id="76" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Adam, at Eve's grave: "Wheresoever she was, THERE was Eden."</quote><quote id="77" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Principles have no real force except when one is well-fed.</quote><quote id="78" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">"I must have a prodigious quantity of mind; it takes me as much as a week sometimes to make it up."</quote><quote id="79" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">They spell it "Vinci" and pronounce it "Vinchy". Foreigners always spell better than they pronounce.</quote><quote id="80" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">I used to worship the mighty genius of Michael Angelo — that man who was great in poetry, painting, sculpture, architecture — great in every thing he undertook. But I do not want Michael Angelo for breakfast — for luncheon — for dinner — for tea — for supper — for between meals. I like a change, occasionally.</quote><quote id="81" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Enough, enough, enough! Say no more! Lump the whole thing! say that the Creator made Italy from designs by Michael Angelo!</quote><quote id="82" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Guides cannot master the subtleties of the American joke.</quote><quote id="83" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">I wish Europe would let Russia annihilate Turkey a little--not much, but enough to make it difficult to find the place again without a divining-rod or a diving-bell.</quote><quote id="84" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Virtue never has been as respectable as money.</quote><quote id="85" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">The people of those foreign countries are very, very ignorant. They looked curiously at the costumes we had brought from the wilds of America. They observed that we talked loudly at table sometimes. They noticed that we looked out for expenses and got what we conveniently could out of a franc, and wondered where in the mischief we came from. In Paris they just simply opened their eyes and stared when we spoke to them in French! We never did succeed in making those idiots understand their own language.</quote><quote id="86" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">"Travel is fatal to prejudice, bigotry, and narrow-mindedness, and many of our people need it sorely on these accounts."</quote><quote id="87" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">The Erie railroad kills 23 to 46; the other 845 railroads kill an average of one-third of a man each; and the rest of that million, amounting in the aggregate to that appalling figure of 987,631 corpses, die naturally in their beds! You will excuse me from taking any more chances on those beds. The railroads are good enough for me.</quote><quote id="88" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Tom appeared on the sidewalk with a bucket of whitewash and a long-handled brush. He surveyed the fence, and all gladness left him and a deep melancholy settled down upon his spirit. Thirty yards of board fence nine feet high. Life to him seemed hollow, and existence but a burden.</quote><quote id="89" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">He had discovered a great law of human action, without knowing it — namely, that in order to make a man or a boy covet a thing, it is only necessary to make the thing difficult to obtain.</quote><quote id="90" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Work consists of whatever a body is OBLIGED to do, and...Play consists of whatever a body is not obliged to do.</quote><quote id="91" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">The minister gave out his text and droned along monotonously through an argument that was so prosy that many a head by and by began to nod — and yet it was an argument that dealt in limitless fire and brimstone and thinned the predestined elect down to a company so small as to be hardly worth the saving.</quote><quote id="92" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">There was no getting around the stubborn fact that taking sweetmeats was only "hooking," while taking bacon and hams and such valuables was plain simple stealing — and there was a command against that in the Bible. So they inwardly resolved that so long as they remained in the business, their piracies should not again be sullied with the crime of stealing.</quote><quote id="93" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">To promise not to do a thing is the surest way in the world to make a body want to go and do that very thing.</quote><quote id="94" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">She makes me get up just at the same time every morning; she makes me wash, they comb me all to thunder; she won't let me sleep in the woodshed; I got to wear them blamed clothes that just smothers me, Tom; they don't seem to let any air git through 'em, somehow; and they're so rotten nice that I can't set down, nor lay down, nor roll around anywher's; I hain't slid on a cellar-door for — well, it 'pears to be years; I got to go to church and sweat and sweat — I hate them ornery sermons! I can't ketch a fly in there, I can't chaw. I got to wear shoes all Sunday. The widder eats by a bell; she goes to bed by a bell; she gits up by a bell — everything's so awful reg'lar a body can't stand it.</quote><quote id="95" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">There is a sumptuous variety about the New England weather that compels the stranger's admiration — and regret. The weather is always doing something there; always attending strictly to business; always getting up new designs and trying them on people to see how they will go. But it gets through more business in spring than in any other season. In the spring I have counted one hundred and thirty-six different kinds of weather inside of twenty-four hours.</quote><quote id="96" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Probable nor'east to sou'west winds, varying to the soutard and westard and eastard and points between; high and low barometer, sweeping round from place to place; probable areas of rain, snow, hail, and drought, succeeded or preceded by earthquakes with thunder and lightning.</quote><quote id="97" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">One of the brightest gems in the New England weather is the dazzling uncertainty of it.</quote><quote id="98" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Persons attempting to find a motive in this narrative will be prosecuted; persons attempting to find a moral in it will be banished; persons attempting to find a plot in it will be shot.
BY ORDER OF THE AUTHOR.</quote><quote id="99" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">You don't know about me without you have read a book by the name of The Adventures of Tom Sawyer; but that ain't no matter. That book was made by Mr. Mark Twain, and he told the truth, mainly. There was things which he stretched, but mainly he told the truth.</quote><quote id="100" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Jim was most ruined for a servant, because he got stuck up on account of having seen the devil and been rode by witches.</quote><quote id="101" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">We catched fish and talked, and we took a swim now and then to keep off sleepiness. It was kind of solemn, drifting down the big, still river, laying on our backs looking up at the stars, and we didn't ever feel like talking loud, and it warn't often that we laughed, only a little kind of a low chuckle. We had mighty good weather as a general thing, and nothing ever happened to us at all, that night, nor the next, nor the next.</quote><quote id="102" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">"Pilgrim's Progress", about a man that left his family, it didn't say why. I read considerable in it now and then. The statements was interesting, but tough.</quote><quote id="103" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">There warn't anybody at the church, except maybe a hog or two, for there warn't any lock on the door, and hogs likes a puncheon floor in summer-time because it's cool. If you notice, most folks don't go to church only when they've got to; but a hog is different.</quote><quote id="104" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">We said there warn't no home like a raft, after all. Other places do seem so cramped up and smothery, but a raft don't. You feel mighty free and easy and comfortable on a raft.</quote><quote id="105" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">To be, or not to be; that is the bare bodkin.</quote><quote id="106" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">H'aint we got all the fools in town on our side? And ain't that a big enough majority in any town?</quote><quote id="107" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">I was a-trembling, because I'd got to decide, forever, betwixt two things, and I knowed it. I studied a minute, sort of holding my breath, and then says to myself, "All right, then, I'll GO to hell."</quote><quote id="108" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">But I reckon I got to light out for the Territory ahead of the rest, because Aunt Sally she's going to adopt me and sivilize me and I can't stand it. I been there before.</quote><quote id="109" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">The citizen who thinks he sees that the commonwealth's political clothes are worn out, and yet holds his peace and does not agitate for a new suit, is disloyal, he is a traitor. That he may be the only one who thinks he sees this decay, does not excuse him: it is his duty to agitate anyway, and it is the duty of others to vote him down if they do not see the matter as he does.</quote><quote id="110" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">My kind of loyalty was loyalty to one's country, not to its institutions or its officeholders. The country is the real thing, the substantial thing, the eternal thing; it is the thing to watch over, and care for, and be loyal to; institutions are extraneous, they are its mere clothing, and clothing can wear out, become ragged, cease to be comfortable, cease to protect the body from winter, disease, and death.</quote><quote id="111" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">The pilgrims were human beings. Otherwise they would have acted differently. They had come a long and difficult journey, and now when the journey was nearly finished, and they learned that the main thing they had come for had ceased to exist, they didn't do as horses or cats or angle-worms would probably have done — turn back and get at something profitable — no, anxious as they had before been to see the miraculous fountain, they were as much as forty times as anxious now to see the place where it had used to be. There is no accounting for human beings.</quote><quote id="112" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Many a small thing has been made large by the right kind of advertising.</quote><quote id="113" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Whenever the literary German dives into a sentence, that is the last you are going to see of him till he emerges on the other side of his Atlantic with his verb in his mouth.</quote><quote id="114" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">You can't depend on your eyes when your imagination is out of focus.</quote><quote id="115" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">The humorous story is told gravely; the teller does his best to conceal the fact that he even dimly suspects that there is anything funny about it.</quote><quote id="116" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">To string incongruities and absurdities together in a wandering and sometimes purposeless way, and seem innocently unaware that they are absurdities, is the basis of the American art, if my position is correct.</quote><quote id="117" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Nothing that grieves us can be called little: by the eternal laws of proportion a child's loss of a doll and a king's loss of a crown are events of the same size.</quote><quote id="118" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">I have no race prejudices nor caste prejudices nor creed prejudices. All I care to know is that a man is a human being, and that is enough for me; he can't be any worse.</quote><quote id="119" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">The Jew is not a disturber of the peace of any country. Even his enemies will concede that. He is not a loafer, he is not a sot, he is not noisy, he is not a brawler nor a rioter, he is not quarrelsome. In the statistics of crime his presence is conspicuously rare — in all countries. With murder and other crimes of violence he has but little to do: he is a stranger to the hangman. In the police court's daily long roll of "assaults" and "drunk and disorderlies" his name seldom appears ...</quote><quote id="120" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">A Jewish beggar is not impossible, perhaps; such a thing may exist, but there are few men that can say they have seen that spectacle.</quote><quote id="121" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">These facts are all on the credit side of the proposition that the Jew is a good and orderly citizen. Summed up, they certify that he is quiet, peaceable, industrious, unaddicted to high crimes and brutal dispositions; that his family life is commendable; that he is not a burden upon public charities; that he is not a beggar; that in benevolence he is above the reach of competition. These are the very quintessentials of good citizenship.</quote><quote id="122" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">If the statistics are right, the Jews constitute but one percent of the human race. It suggests a nebulous dim puff of star dust lost in the blaze of the Milky Way. Properly the Jew ought hardly to be heard of, but he is heard of, has always been heard of. He is as prominent on the planet as any other people, and his commercial importance is extravagantly out of proportion to the smallness of his bulk. His contributions to the world's list of great names in literature, science, art, music, finance, medicine, and abstruse learning are also away out of proportion to the weakness of his numbers. He has made a marvellous fight in the world, in all the ages; and has done it with his hands tied behind him. He could be vain of himself, and be excused for it. The Egyptian, the Babylonian, and the Persian rose, filled the planet with sound and splendor, then faded to dream-stuff and passed away; the Greek and the Roman followed, and made a vast noise, and they are gone; other peoples have sprung up and held their torch high for a time, but it burned out, and they sit in twilight now, or have vanished. The Jew saw them all, beat them all, and is now what he always was, exhibiting no decadence, no infirmities of age, no weakening of his parts, no slowing of his energies, no dulling of his alert and aggressive mind. All things are mortal but the Jew; all other forces pass, but he remains. What is the secret of his immortality?</quote><quote id="123" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Everybody's private motto: It's better to be popular than right.</quote><quote id="124" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">It may be called the Master Passion, the hunger for self-approval.</quote><quote id="125" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">The fact that man knows right from wrong proves his "intellectual" superiority to the other creatures; but the fact that he can "do" wrong proves his "moral" inferiority to any creature that "cannot".</quote><quote id="126" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">But the truth is, that when a Library expels a book of mine and leaves an unexpurgated Bible lying around where unprotected youth and age can get hold of it, the deep unconscious irony of it delights me and doesn't anger me.</quote><quote id="127" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Citizenship? We have none! In place of it we teach patriotism which Samuel Johnson said a hundred and forty or a hundred and fifty years ago was the last refuge of the scoundrel -- and I believe that he was right. I remember when I was a boy and I heard repeated time and time again the phrase, 'My country, right or wrong, my country!' How absolutely absurd is such an idea. How absolutely absurd to teach this idea to the youth of the country.</quote><quote id="128" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Herodotus says, "Very few things happen at the right time, and the rest do not happen at all. The conscientious historian will correct these defects".</quote><quote id="129" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">A gifted person ought to learn English (barring spelling and pronouncing) in thirty hours, French in thirty days, and German in thirty years.</quote><quote id="130" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">We have not the reverent feeling for the rainbow that the savage has, because we know how it is made. We have lost as much as we gained by prying into that matter.</quote><quote id="131" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">You may say a cat uses good grammar. Well, a cat does -- but you let a cat get excited once; you let a cat get to pulling fur with another cat on a shed, nights, and you'll hear grammar that will give you the lockjaw. Ignorant people think it's the noise which fighting cats make that is so aggravating, but it ain't so; it's the sickening grammar they use.</quote><quote id="132" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">He [Mark Twain] spoke of humor, and thought it must be one of the chief attributes of God. He cited plants and animals that were distinctly humorous in form and in their characteristics. These he declared were God’s jokes.</quote><quote id="133" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">"There has never been a just one, never an honorable one — on the part of the instigator of the war." I can see a million years ahead, and this rule will never change in so many as half a dozen instances. The loud little handful — as usual — will shout for the war. The pulpit will — warily and cautiously — object — at first; the great, big, dull bulk of the nation will rub its sleepy eyes and try to make out why there should be a war, and will say, earnestly and indignantly, "It is unjust and dishonorable, and there is no necessity for it." Then the handful will shout louder. A few fair men on the other side will argue and reason against the war with speech and pen, and at first will have a hearing and be applauded; but it will not last long; those others will outshout them, and presently the anti-war audiences will thin out and lose popularity. Before long you will see this curious thing: the speakers stoned from the platform, and free speech strangled by hordes of furious men who in their secret hearts are still at one with those stoned speakers — as earlier — but do not dare to say so. And now the whole nation — pulpit and all — will take up the war-cry, and shout itself hoarse, and mob any honest man who ventures to open his mouth; and presently such mouths will cease to open. Next the statesmen will invent cheap lies, putting the blame upon the nation that is attacked, and every man will be glad of those conscience-soothing falsities, and will diligently study them, and refuse to examine any refutations of them; and thus he will by and by convince himself that the war is just, and will thank God for the better sleep he enjoys after this process of grotesque self-deception.</quote><quote id="134" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">"Only laughter can blow [a colossal humbug] to rags and atoms at a blast. Against the assault of laughter nothing can stand."</quote><quote id="135" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">There is no God, no universe, no human race, no earthly life, no heaven, no hell. It is all a Dream, a grotesque and foolish dream. Nothing exists but you. And "You are but a Thought — a vagrant Thought, a useless Thought, a homeless Thought, wandering forlorn among the empty eternities."</quote><quote id="136" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">The bicycle had what is called the 'wabbles', and had them very badly. In order to keep my position, a good many things were required of me, and in every instance the thing required was against nature. Against nature, but not against the laws of nature.</quote><quote id="137" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Try as you may, you don't get down as you would from a horse, you get down as you would from a house afire. You make a spectacle of yourself every time.</quote><quote id="138" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">The self-taught man seldom knows anything accurately, and he does not know a tenth as much as he could have known if he had worked under teachers;</quote><quote id="139" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">There are those who imagine that the unlucky accidents of life—life's "experiences"—are in some way useful to us. I wish I could find out how. I never know one of them to happen twice. They always change off and swap around and catch you on your inexperienced side.</quote><quote id="140" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Before taking final leave of me, my instructor inquired concerning my physical strength, and I was able to inform him that I hadn't any.</quote><quote id="141" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">I started out alone to seek adventures. You don't really have to seek them—that is nothing but a phrase—they come to you.</quote><quote id="142" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">I have seen it stated that no expert is quick enough to run over a dog; that a dog is always able to skip out of his way. I think that that may be true; but I think that the reason he couldn't run over the dog was because he was trying to. I did not try to run over any dog. But I ran over every dog that came along.</quote><quote id="143" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">"Get a bicycle. You will not regret it, if you live."</quote><quote id="144" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">We began to stir against slavery. Hearts grew soft, here, there, and yonder. There was no place in the land where the seeker could not find some small budding sign of pity for the slave. No place in all the land but one—the pulpit. It yielded at last; it always does. It fought a strong and stubborn fight, and then did what it always does, joined the procession—at the tail end. Slavery fell. The slavery text remained; the practice changed, that was all.</quote><quote id="145" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">During many ages there were witches. The Bible said so. the Bible commanded that they should not be allowed to live. Therefore the Church, after eight hundred years, gathered up its halters, thumb-screws, and firebrands, and set about its holy work in earnest. She worked hard at it night and day during nine centuries and imprisoned, tortured, hanged, and burned whole hordes and armies of witches, and washed the Christian world clean with their foul blood. Then it was discovered that there was no such thing as witches, and never had been. One does not know whether to laugh or to cry. Who discovered that there was no such thing as a witch—the priest, the parson? No, these never discover anything. … There are no witches. The witch text remains; only the practice has changed. Hell fire is gone, but the text remains. Infant damnation is gone, but the text remains. More than two hundred death penalties are gone from the law books, but the texts that authorized them remain.</quote><quote id="146" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Biographies are but clothes and buttons of the man — the biography of the man himself cannot be written.</quote><quote id="147" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Of all the creatures that were made he [man] is the most detestable. Of the entire brood he is the only one — the solitary one — that possesses malice. That is the basest of all instincts, passions, vices — the most hateful...He is the only creature that inflicts pain for sport, knowing it to "be" pain...Also — in all the list he is the only creature that has a nasty mind.</quote><quote id="148" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">The trade of critic, in literature, music, and the drama, is the most degraded of all trades.</quote><quote id="149" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">There are people who strictly deprive themselves of each and every eatable, drinkable and smokable which has in any way acquired a shady reputation. They pay this price for health. And health is all they get for it. How strange it is. It is like paying out your whole fortune for a cow that has gone dry.</quote><quote id="150" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">In religion and politics, people's beliefs and convictions are in almost every case gotten at second-hand, and without examination, from authorities who have not themselves examined the questions at issue, but have taken them at second-hand from other non-examiners, whose opinions about them were not worth a brass farthing.</quote><quote id="151" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">France has neither winter nor summer nor morals. Apart from these drawbacks it is a fine country.</quote><quote id="152" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">God's inhumanity to man makes countless thousands mourn.</quote><quote id="153" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">France has usually been governed by prostitutes.</quote><quote id="154" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">The radical invents the views. When he has worn them out the conservative adopts them.</quote><quote id="155" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Familiarity breeds contempt — and children.</quote><quote id="156" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Good breeding consists in concealing how much we think of ourselves and how little we think of the other person.</quote><quote id="157" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Nature knows no indecencies; man invents them.</quote><quote id="158" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Death, the only immortal who treats us all alike, whose pity and whose peace and whose refuge are for all — the soiled and the pure, the rich and the poor, the loved and the unloved.</quote><quote id="159" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Surely the test of a novel's characters is that you feel a strong interest in them and their affairs—the good to be successful, the bad to suffer failure. Well, in John Ward, you feel "no" divided interest, no discriminating interest—you want them all to land in hell together, and right away.</quote><quote id="160" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">None but the dead have free speech.</quote><quote id="161" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Some men worship rank, some worship heroes, some worship power, some worship God, &amp; over these ideals they dispute &amp; cannot unite — but they all worship money.</quote><quote id="162" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">You can't depend on your judgment when your imagination is out of focus.</quote><quote id="163" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Education consists mainly in what we have unlearned.</quote><quote id="164" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Only one thing is impossible for God: To find any sense in any copyright law on the planet.</quote><quote id="165" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Whenever you find that you are on the side of the majority, it is time to reform.</quote><quote id="166" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Geological time is not money. A pity too; for it would have abolished poverty from the earth. Let us adopt geological time, then time being money, — there will be no more poverty. We are all missionaries (propagandists of our views). Each of us disapproves of the other missionaries; in fact detests them, as a rule. I am one of the herd myself. It is noticeable that the professional always uses the one license: "Go ye into all the world," and ignores the Golden Rule which would restrain him from entering China and one or two other countries where he is not wanted and is not welcome.</quote><quote id="167" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Not a single right is indestructible: a new might can at any time abolish it, hence, man possesses not a single "permanent" right. 
 God is Might (and He is shifty, malicious, and uncertain).</quote><quote id="168" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">"In God We Trust." It is the choicest compliment that has ever been paid us, and the most gratifying to our feelings. It is simple, direct, gracefully phrased: it always sounds well —</quote><quote id="169" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">"In the beginning of a change, the patriot is a scarce man, and brave, and hated and scorned. When his cause succeeds, the timid join him, for then it costs nothing to be a patriot"</quote><quote id="170" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Against our traditions we are now entering upon an unjust and trivial war, a war against a helpless people, and for a base object — robbery. At first our citizens spoke out against this thing, by an impulse natural to their training. Today they have turned, and their voice is the other way. What caused the change? Merely a politician's trick — a high-sounding phrase, a blood-stirring phrase which turned their uncritical heads: "Our Country, right or wrong!" An empty phrase, a silly phrase. It was shouted by every newspaper, it was thundered from the pulpit, the Superintendent of Public Instruction placarded it in every schoolhouse in the land, the War Department inscribed it upon the flag. And every man who failed to shout it or who was silent, was proclaimed a traitor — none but those others were patriots. To be a patriot, one had to say, and keep on saying, "Our Country, right or wrong," and urge on the little war. Have you not perceived that that phrase is an insult to the nation? 
For in a republic, who is "the Country"? Is it the Government which is for the moment in the saddle? Why, the Government is merely a servant — merely a temporary servant; it cannot be its prerogative to determine what is right and what is wrong, and decide who is a patriot and who isn't. Its function is to obey orders, not originate them. Who, then, is "the country?" Is it the newspaper? Is it the pulpit? Is it the school-superintendent? Why, these are mere parts of the country, not the whole of it; they have not command, they have only their little share in the command. They are but one in the thousand; it is in the thousand that command is lodged; they must determine what is right and what is wrong; they must decide who is a patriot and who isn’t.</quote><quote id="171" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">In a monarchy, the king and his family are the country; in a republic it is the common voice of the people. Each of you, for himself, by himself and on his own responsibility, must speak. And it is a solemn and weighty responsibility, and not lightly to be flung aside at the bullying of pulpit, press, government, or the empty catch-phrases of politicians. Each must for himself alone decide what is right and what is wrong, and which course is patriotic and which isn't. You cannot shirk this and be a man. To decide it against your convictions is to be an unqualified and inexcusable traitor, both to yourself and to your country, let men label you as they may. If you alone of all the nation shall decide one way, and that way be the right way according to your convictions of the right, you have done your duty by yourself and by your country — hold up your head! You have nothing to be ashamed of. 
Only when a republic's life is in danger should a man uphold his government when it is in the wrong. There is no other time. 
This Republic's life is not in peril. The nation has sold its honor for a phrase. It has swung itself loose from its safe anchorage and is drifting, its helm is in pirate hands.</quote><quote id="172" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Drawing on my fine command of language, I said nothing.</quote><quote id="173" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Few sinners are saved after the first twenty minutes of a sermon.</quote><quote id="174" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">I don't give a damn for a man that can only spell a word one way.</quote><quote id="175" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Only presidents, editors and people with tapeworms have the right to use the editorial "we".</quote><quote id="176" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Never let your schooling interfere with your education.</quote><quote id="177" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">I can teach anybody how to get what they want out of life. The problem is I can't find anybody who can tell me what they want.</quote><quote id="178" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">I was born intelligent, education ruined me.</quote><quote id="179" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Patriotism is supporting your country all the time, and your government when it deserves it.</quote><quote id="180" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">If voting made any difference they wouldn't let us do it.</quote><quote id="181" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">All you have to fear is your mother's cooking.</quote><quote id="182" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Sometimes I wonder whether the world is being run by smart people who are putting us on, or by imbeciles who really mean it.</quote><quote id="183" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">The past does not repeat itself, but it rhymes.</quote><quote id="184" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">To my embarrassment, I was born in bed with a lady.</quote><quote id="185" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">A lie can make it half way around the world before the truth has time to put its boots on.</quote><quote id="186" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Often, the less there is to justify a traditional custom, the harder it is to get rid of it.</quote><quote id="187" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">{{anchor|mine}} A mine is a hole in the ground owned by a liar.</quote><quote id="188" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Fiction is obliged to stick to possibilities; truth is not.</quote><quote id="189" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">It ain't what you don't know that gets you into trouble. It's what you know for sure that just ain't so.</quote><quote id="190" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">If you don't like the weather in New England, just wait a few minutes.</quote><quote id="191" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Figures don't lie, but liars figure.</quote><quote id="192" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Every generalization is false, including this one.</quote><quote id="193" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">I've never killed a man, but I've read many an obituary with a great deal of satisfaction.</quote><quote id="194" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">I admire the serene assurance of those who have religious faith. It is wonderful to observe the calm confidence of a Christian with four aces.</quote><quote id="195" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">I do not fear death. I had been dead for billions and billions of years before I was born, and had not suffered the slightest inconvenience from it.</quote><quote id="196" author="Mark Twain" cats="1910s deaths|Californians|Humorists|Journalists|Missourians|Novelists|Short story writers" ref="">Keep away from people who try to belittle your ambitions. Small people always do that, but the really great make you feel that you, too, can become great.</quote></quotes>